<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True relation of the ground, occasion, and circumstances of that horrible murther committed by Iohn Bartram, gent. vpon the body of Sir Iohn Tyndham of Lincolns Inne, knight, one of the masters of the honorable Court of Chancery, the twelfth day of this instant Nouemb. written by way of letter from a gentleman, to his country friend ; together with The examination of the said Bartram, taken before the right honourable, Sir Fra. Bacon knight, His Maiesties Atturney Generall, and Sir Henry Yelnerton knight, His Maiesties Solliciter General, according to speciall directions giuen by His Maiestie in that behalfe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14054.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20214070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20214070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1709:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True relation of the ground, occasion, and circumstances of that horrible murther committed by Iohn Bartram, gent. vpon the body of Sir Iohn Tyndham of Lincolns Inne, knight, one of the masters of the honorable Court of Chancery, the twelfth day of this instant Nouemb. written by way of letter from a gentleman, to his country friend ; together with The examination of the said Bartram, taken before the right honourable, Sir Fra. Bacon knight, His Maiesties Atturney Generall, and Sir Henry Yelnerton knight, His Maiesties Solliciter General, according to speciall directions giuen by His Maiestie in that behalfe.</title>
                  <author>N. T.</author>
                  <author>N. I.</author>
                  <author>N. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Special t.p.: The examination of John Bartram.</note>
                  <note>Part I signed at end: N.T.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to N.I. by STC (2nd ed.). Another copy (STC 14054) is signed: N.J.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tyndham, John, d. 1616.</term>
               <term>Bartram, John.  d. 1616.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THE GROVND, Occaſion, and Circumſtances, of that <hi>horrible Murther committed by</hi> IOHN BARTRAM, Gent. vpon the body of Sir IOHN TYNDAL of <hi>Lincolns Inne,</hi> Knight: One of the Maſters of the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> the twelfth day of this inſtant <hi>Nouemb.</hi> Written by way of Letter from a Gentleman, to his Country friend.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Together with the Examination of the ſaid Bartram,</hi> taken before the right Honourable, Sir <hi>Fra. Bacon</hi> Knight, his Maieſties Atturney Generall: and Sir <hi>Henry Yeluerton</hi> Knight, his Maieſties Solliciter <hi>General, according to ſpeciall directions giuen by his Maieſtie in that behalfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Beale,</hi> 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:2"/>
                  <head>A True Relation of THE GROVND, Occaſion, and Circumſtances, of <hi>that horrible Murther committed by</hi> IOHN BARTRAM, Gent. vpon the body of Sir IOHN TYNDALL of <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> Knight, One of the Maſters of the Hon<hi rend="sup">rable</hi> Court of CHANCERY, the twelfth day of this inſtant <hi>Nouember.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O ſtreames run ſwifter then the rumors of vnhappy accidents; though it oft falleth out that the faſter they run the more troubled their current is.</p>
                  <p>You cannot but haue heard of the cruell mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and maſſacre of Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> wrought by the wicked and bloudy hand of <hi>Iohn Bartram;</hi> But
<pb facs="tcp:23837:3"/>
I feare that different humours in their relations, haue ſet ſeuerall ſtamps vpon the fact: ſome fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing circumſtances that fell not out; ſome knowing neither the number nor the truth of them; ſome neglecting to divulge the particulars; and ſome mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting errour in the report, are rather filled with wonder at the action, then with hatred of it. You ſhall heereby in a ſhort period, haue the corne win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed from the chaffe, and reall truth brought you, without either mixture or addition of fancy or falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: being drawne from them that beſt knew it, and had beſt cauſe to vnderſtand it: wherein you ſhall ſee, how neglected ſparkes lurking in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt heart, will ſoone breake into flames of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
                  <p>One <hi>Leonard Camberlin,</hi> about ſeuen yeeres paſt dying without iſſue, and without Will, there was obtained for <hi>Anne Chamberlin,</hi> then an infant, his brothers daughter, by the practiſe and labour of Sir <hi>Phillip Scudamore,</hi> an adminiſtration of <hi>Leonards</hi> goods: This <hi>Anne</hi> was neither priuie to it, nor had profit by it; but by this meanes the perſonall eſtate of <hi>Leonard,</hi> fell into the fingers of Sir <hi>Phillip,</hi> who when hee had ſifted the eſtate thoroughly, ſhifted himſelfe our of the kingdome, and being ill affected to the Religion here, pretended to gaine the liberty of an euill conſcience beyond the Seas, where he died a Papiſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23837:3"/>
                     <hi>Iohn Bartram</hi> hauing married the halfe ſiſter of <hi>Leonard,</hi> in the behalfe of his wife, obtaines a repeale of the Adminiſtration granted to <hi>Anne,</hi> and had it committed to his wife as of right it ought.</p>
                  <p>When he had thus gotten the Adminiſtration, he and his wife complaine in Chancery againſt <hi>Anne Chamberlin,</hi> that ſhee might diſcouer the true eſtate of <hi>Leonard</hi> the Inteſtate, and haue the ſame by order of that Court ſet ouer to them.</p>
                  <p>Heerevpon <hi>Anne</hi> maketh her anſwere vpon her Oath, but is able to diſcouer no particulars of the eſtate, neither in debts nor otherwiſe, for nothing came to her hands, but all was latcht in the hands of Sir <hi>Phillip Scudamore</hi> in pretence of her right, as Adminiſtratrix. But <hi>Bartram</hi> deſcending to proofes in this ſute, had the preciſe teſtimony of two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that there was due to <hi>Leonards Chamberlins</hi> eſtate from one <hi>Harris</hi> vpon all bonds, accompts, reckonings, and ſpecialties, 200. pound.</p>
                  <p>The Cauſe comming to hearing, the Lord <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> (in his Honorable Iuſtice) minding that <hi>Bartra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> ſhould haue from <hi>Anne Chamberlin,</hi> ſo much of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards</hi> eſtate as was proued in Court (which was 22. pound) vpon all bonds and reckonings from <hi>Harris</hi> and no more: And ſo pronouncing his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, by the error and ſlip of the Regiſter, it was ſet downe, and penned that a bond of 200. pound made by <hi>Harris</hi> to the Inteſtate ſhould bee by <hi>Anne</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23837:4"/>
deliuered to <hi>Bartram</hi> and his wife.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bartram</hi> herein eſpying his aduantage, hotly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues the decree, to haue a particular bond of 200. pound brought in Court and deliuered: which when <hi>Anne</hi> examined therevpon, could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, excuſing her ſelfe by Sir <hi>Phillip Scudamores</hi> catching into his hands, of all the bonds and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties due to <hi>Leonard</hi> the Inteſtate, ſhee was ordered by the Court to bring in the 200. pound, and to pay the ſame to <hi>Bartram</hi> and his wife; which ſhee did, and they had it.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Bartram</hi> ſaw hee had caught the prey, hee neuer hunted, and had the two hundred pound in his purſe, as due vpon a particular bond, which was neither confeſſed by the partie, nor proued by the witneſſes; that this <hi>Sent</hi> might die, in his craftie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, hee would not too eagarly follow the Chaſe; but ſleepes vpon this many moneths, before he ſets his foot forward in this ſuit againe.</p>
                  <p>A yeere after he reneues his cry, and moues the Court: That becauſe it ſtood proued, that vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers accompts, bonds, reckonings, and ſpecialties, there was due from <hi>Harris</hi> to <hi>Leonard</hi> the Inteſtate, the ſumme of two hundred pound; therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that <hi>Anne</hi> the defendant (at this time married to Sir <hi>George Symons</hi>) might bring thoſe into the Court to be deliuered to him and his wife which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord <hi>Chancellor</hi> accordingly, and a day
<pb facs="tcp:23837:4"/>
certaine giuen for performance thereof.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Bartram</hi> ſaw the day paſt, and the Order not performed, hee eagerly ſues forth vpon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant <hi>Annes</hi> contempt, the ordinary proces of the Court, till it came to proclamation of Rebellion: And though hee might haue ſeene himſelfe checkt by the hand of God, in taking her to reſt, who liued a reſtleſſe life, by his diſquieting her in ſutes, yet doth he not deſiſt, but ſeeing her cloſed vp in the earth, hunts her husband Sir <hi>George Symons</hi> till hee brings him to the bay, and then layes hold on him as for a contempt, in not bringing in his wife while ſhee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the Law ſuppoſing euery wife ameſnable at the will of her husband, and by order of the Court in the Iuſtice of it, gets him committed to the fleete, where he hath remained in the nature of a priſoner, from Hillary terme laſt, till the laſt day of this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas Terme.</p>
                  <p>Now Sir <hi>George Symons</hi> finding himſelfe thus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlayed by his aduerſary <hi>Bartram,</hi> and that his hawkes eye watcht now to make him his prey: pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioneth to the Lord <hi>Chauncellor,</hi> and humbly by way of motion alſo deſireth, that the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the cauſe may be reuiewed; the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the defendant <hi>Anne</hi> vpon her oath while ſhee liued may be conſidered, and the proofes compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to ſee if any particular bond of two hundred pound, or if any double ſumme of two hundred
<pb facs="tcp:23837:5"/>
pound were proued; inforcing, that <hi>Bartram</hi> had already in his purſe as much as any way was war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by proofe.</p>
                  <p>The Lord <hi>Chauncellor</hi> ſomewhat compaſſionate herein, and as in all caſes, ſo eſpecially being tender to reſtraine the ſubiect of his libertie, vnleſſe hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre ſome manifeſt contempt, was pleaſed herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to referre the ſame to Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Doctor <hi>Amye,</hi> two auncient Maſters of the Court, that they ſhould certifie to him the whole merits of the cauſe, yet kept himſelfe euen in the courſe of Iuſtice, not enlarging Sir <hi>George Symons,</hi> vpon this ſuggeſtion, but allowing his liberty vpon Reconuſance to appeare from day to day.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon <hi>Bartram</hi> according to the courſe of the Court, exhibited Interrogatories to Sir <hi>George Symons,</hi> touching the contempt by him &amp; his wife; who vpon examination was found to be priuy, and acquainted with the proceſſe that went forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wife, and thereby was in truth in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for not bringing <hi>her</hi> into <hi>Court:</hi> But hee would not examine Sir <hi>George</hi> whether hee had any bils, accompts, reckonings, bonds, or ſpecialties, due or belonging to <hi>Leonard Chamberlins</hi> eſtate, which when the two Maſters of the Court perceiued, they asked him, why hee did not examine Sir <hi>George</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that point: and hee anſwered, it was needleſſe, for he thought in his conſcience, and was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:23837:5"/>
ir <hi>George</hi> had none of them. Yet you ſee with what violence he both takes him, holds him, and keepes him.</p>
                  <p>Now when Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> and Maſter Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Amy,</hi> had exactly with great paines, and with often ſearch ſought out, and found the true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of this cauſe, they returned their report into the Court the fourth day of this preſent Nouember, in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>That vpon due peruſall and conſideration both of <hi>Anſwere, Confeſsion,</hi> and <hi>proofes,</hi> in the Cauſe they did find, there was but one two hundred pound in all due: But that vpon the eager purſuit of <hi>Bartram,</hi> Sir <hi>George Symons</hi> had ſuffered long impriſonment; And they thought it time he were releaſed, which notwithſtanding they referred to the better iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court.</p>
                  <p>In which report you may note three things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt that the matter of it was iuſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly that it had no bitterneſſe in it, more then well became Iudges, who ought not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſencible when they find the Court had beene made an inſtrument of any mans cauſeleſſe ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that it was not concluding or peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, but left the matter to the iudgement of the Court.</p>
                  <p>When this report was returned into Court, there was nothing ſuddenly done vpon it, but day was
<pb facs="tcp:23837:6"/>
giuen to <hi>Bartram</hi> vntill Tueſday the twelfth of this Moneth, to ſhew cauſe, why Sir <hi>George</hi> ſhould not be enlarged, and himſelfe diſmiſſed out of Court.</p>
                  <p>Now when <hi>Bartram</hi> ſaw this bitte put into his mouth, whereby his couetous deſire was bridled, and his imaginary hopes loſt, which was to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother two hundred pound, to which hee had no colour of right; his heart begins to ſwell: And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this iuſt report as a ſhield to defend Sir <hi>George Symons</hi> from his purſuit, hee turnes his fury another way, and caſts his reſolution of Reuenge vpon Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> whoſe perſon while he liued was,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Of great reputation for his integrity:</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of great reſpect for his temperance and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the place he held:</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Of good opinion for his learning and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Much to bee reuerenced both for his birth, paines, and his age.</p>
                  <p>Yet neither his age, nor his paines, nor his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, nor his integritie, could bee any arguments for <hi>Bartram</hi> to ſpare him, or any buckler againſt his bloudy violence.</p>
                  <p>Wherein you ſhall ſee what ſpurres the diuell ſets to his heeles to haſten him to hell.</p>
                  <p>He before coueted but money, or bonds from Sir <hi>George Symons;</hi> now that ſparke is quenched, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter flame ariſeth: nothing now will quench his
<pb facs="tcp:23837:6"/>
thirſt, but the bloud of Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall:</hi> See now the ſteps he ſeekes to tread, and you ſhall perceiue this action of his had,
<list>
                        <item>1 Crafty preparation.</item>
                        <item>2 Wicked reſolution.</item>
                        <item>3 Helliſh execution.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 He ſtrips himſelfe of his eſtate, and the eight day of this moneth hee makes a voluntary deed of gift of all his goods, to one Maſter <hi>Drake,</hi> with whom hee confeſſed hee had no acquaintance. When this deede came to ſealing, hee would haue had the Scriuener dated the ſame, as if it had beene made in <hi>Iuly</hi> before, which he did of craft to defraud his Maieſty of the forfeiture of his goods, he knew would follow vpon the villany of his fact: but no importunitie could winne the Scriuener to that diſhoneſty.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Being thus turned naked, hee now clad himſelfe onely with malice, and opportunity to reuenge: and the tenth day which was Sunday, there is a noyſe of bloud ſounding in his head, and then as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed before the Honourable Iudges of the Kings Bench, he reſolued to kill Sir <hi>Iohn Tindall,</hi> as if hee ſhould murmur to himſelfe; Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath bereaued me of my vniuſt hopes, therefore hee ſhall die an vniuſt death.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Beeing ſetled in this mad reſolution to ſhedde bloud, on the eleuenth of this moneth, the engine
<pb facs="tcp:23837:7"/>
of death muſt be thought of. And that muſt be,
<list>
                        <item>1 Not a ſword: for his old withered hand could not weild it.</item>
                        <item>2 Not a dagger: for he could not be ſure of his ayme, and by that hee might perhaps ſtab him, but not kill him.</item>
                        <item>3 But a Piſtoll muſt bee the executioner. And why? firſt, it is eaſie to handle: ſecondly, it is ſhot off before it be ſeene: thirdly, it teares the body, and carries the life away with it.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>The inſtrument of death being thus thought of, he ſcoureth his Piſtol, layes his bullets ready, which as hee ſaid, had lyen ruſting by him ſixe yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and now muſt be ſcoured to act this tragedy.</p>
                  <p>On the twelfth of this Moneth, beeing the day when <hi>Bartram</hi> by his Counſell ſhould ſhew cauſe to the Court why Sir <hi>George</hi> ſhould not be enlarged, and himſelfe diſmiſſed, hee retained no other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller then the Deuill, who as you may feare by the ſequell, (leauing ſecret things to God) had the Fee he euer ſeekes for, the ſoule of <hi>Bartram</hi> for the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell giuen him.</p>
                  <p>Now this day, firſt hee beſtirres him earely to ſeeke out Maſter <hi>Drake,</hi> to whom hee had giuen his goods, carries his deede with him, carries by a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter after him, his beſt gowne and beſt cloake, comes to Maſter <hi>Drakes</hi> houſe, deliuers him the deed and the goods brought by them (as he ſaid) put him in
<pb facs="tcp:23837:7"/>
poſſeſſion of all the reſt This done, hee ſtayes not, but haſtes againe to Weſtminſter, where miſſing his opportunity to worke his reuenge, about eleuen of the clocke the ſame day, hee betakes him to a Skuller vpon the Thames, and in the way betweene Weſtminſter and the Temple, he ſhootes of his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll (as he ſaid) to ſcoure it, hauing onely powder in it, which no ſooner went off, but hee charged it againe with double bullet, and cloſely carrying it by his ſide, landed at the Temple ſtaires, went vp to Lincolns Inne, awaited at the gate the alighting of Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall</hi> from his Coach, met him going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Chamber, affronts him, complaines his backe was broken by his Report, yet (as hee ſaide) moued Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> the matter might bee put to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premiſe, to which the Knight, nothing ſuſpecting the traine laide for him, anſwered onely (as <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram</hi> confeſſed) <hi>What a Compremiſe now?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereeupon, as Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> was entering into his Chamber, this man poſſeſt with a murdrous Deuil, taking that anſwer of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> as a ſcorne, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Piſtoll vpon him, not before him, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, ſhot him through, ſo as inſtantly he fell downe, and with a groane only ended his life.</p>
                  <p>Company ſoone came in, but Sir <hi>Iohn Tindalls</hi> man ſtricken into a maze, was not able at firſt eyther with his hand to lay hold on the offender, or by his ſpeech to diſcouer him: for <hi>Bartram</hi> had caſt the
<pb facs="tcp:23837:8"/>
Piſtoll from him, yet he haſted not away but ſtood ſtill, no ſtraunger comming in ſuſpecting him, his hoary haires carried ſo graue a ſhew.</p>
                  <p>But after a little pauſe, Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> man gaining his ſpirits againe, and <hi>Bartram</hi> ſeeing hee could not bee hid, reuealed himſelfe, and withall ſtabd himſelfe with a pocket dagger, but the vigilant eye of Sir <hi>Peter Hayman</hi> inſtantly taking hold of his arme, ſo dulled the ſtroake, as that the hurt was not great, which this wretch perceiuing, with his left arme drew forth a knife, (hauing prepared alſo a double weapon of death for himſelfe,) and offered again to deſtroy himſelfe, but was likewiſe preuented.</p>
                  <p>Now alas Sir, you ſee there was in trueth no words of prouocation in the anſwer of Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> and who knew his countenance muſt ſay, it was euer milde and pleaſing, not lofty nor ſower. But malice that carries a man out of himſelfe, makes euery ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect ſeeme vglye, and euery word ſound harſh, more ſpeedily to thruſt on reuenge. Howbeit in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe, you may obſerue many things which might haue made <hi>Bartram</hi> hatefull to himſelfe, and which will ſtill keep him liuing as a Monſter of men, and as a ſcorne to poſterity. For you ſee,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The ground of his Malice was vniuſt: ſtirred vp by a iuſt report, as hath beene ſhewed before.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If offence had beene in the Report, hee ſhould not haue beene his owne Reuenger, but haue ſought
<pb facs="tcp:23837:8"/>
redreſſe at a higher hand: the Lord Chancellor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer deafe to any iuſt complaint.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 He wreakes his Malice before the Report did hurt him: for it was not then decreed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Fourthly, he did it ſuddenly and vnſuſpected, vnder a ſhew of treaty and conference.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 He did it trecherouſly and cruelly, diſcharging it behind his backe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Age aſſaulted age, which is not vſuall, each of them being 75. yeeres old at leaſt.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Obſerue the place: It was in an Honorable and ciuill ſociety, where euery man there, thinkes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe within his Caſtell.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 It was done not with a ſingle, but with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bullet, as if hee had thought his fleſh to haue beene of ſteele; or as if his malice meant not onely to murder him, but to mangle him.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 In this deſperate fury, his malice turned her edge vpon himſelfe, and he ſought to haue beene his owne Butcher, but that his Maſter the Diuell <hi>(mercy not Interuenient)</hi> reſerued him as for the place of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> ſo for the end of <hi>Iudas</hi> to be his owne hangman.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Which is moſt remarkeable herein, he made a duellum and aſſault not onely vpon a iuſt man, but euen vpon <hi>Iuſtice it ſelfe,</hi> which the Diuel could not vaunt of in many Ages before, and which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fearefull in example: For all the Iudges of the land, yea, all the Noble Counſellors of State, if
<pb facs="tcp:23837:9"/>
they conſult but with their owne humane weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may in feare, of that man values moſt, which is his life, let fall and vnlooſe their courage in doing Iuſtice, leaſt he that thinkes himſelfe wrongd, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the like Repaſt for them, which <hi>Bartram</hi> heere did for Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Howbeit I hope ſuch feares ſhall vaniſh, for ſure God who is the preſeruer of men, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Iuſtice which is the bond of mans ſocietie to bee broken, but though by this execrable Action one linke bee fallen, yet the chaine is whole, and hee will ſtill increaſe it both in ſtrength and beautie.</p>
                  <p>Againe, forbeare to cenſure the manner of Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndals</hi> death: ſpeed of death is not alway a Iudgement, nor the ſuddenneſſe of it ſuſpicious, where it findes a man in the way of Righteouſnes: but argues anger, when it takes a man in an act of ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> was at this time walking in his Calling appointed by God; and <hi>Bartram</hi> in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling appointed by the Diuell. Heere what <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayes, and it will both ſtay your heart, and ſet ſtrait your iudgement, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.17. <hi>There is a iuſt man that periſheth in his iuſtice, and there is a wicked man that continueth long in his malice:</hi> And though his reckoning be not yet, yet ſtripes and plagues do wait vpon his account.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You</hi> ſee and may perſwade your ſelfe, that Sir
<pb facs="tcp:23837:9"/>
                     <hi>Iohn,</hi> paying that debt to God, which was due to Nature, and being by a malicious hand offered vp as a ſacrifice, both for his Iuſtice, and in his Iuſtice, had the Angels his attendants to carry him to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for there is reſt to the children of God. And as for <hi>Bartram,</hi> (though it be ſafeſt to leaue his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to God; yet if the tree be iudged by the fruit, it being both corrupt and rotten, we may ſay it was neere to burning.</p>
                  <p>But I will returne to <hi>Bartram</hi> liuing: This dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable murther was preſently ſpread abroad; and at the firſt it was as ſtrangely voyced as committed: For fame taking holde no doubt of the obſtinate carriage of <hi>Bartram</hi> without remorſe; and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Induration of his heart to proceed from ſome great Iniuſtice done him by Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall:</hi> blazed it abroad as if hee had beene but a kinde of ſcourge of God vpon an vnrighteous Iudge: and that though he was not to bee Iuſtified in the <hi>Fact,</hi> yet he was to be pittied in his <hi>wrong:</hi> So as that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which was firſt a ſpirit of Malice in the heart of <hi>Bartram,</hi> turnd it ſelfe into the ſpirit of Errour in the mouthes of men.</p>
                  <p>But the firſt thing that was done in proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this foule Murder, was, that the Iudges of the Kings Bench tooke examination of the fact: And being doubtfull that his hurts were dangerous, and deſirous that an examplar Iuſtice ſhould not by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident
<pb facs="tcp:23837:10"/>
be preuented, gaue order he ſhould be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily indited and arraigned. Maiſter <hi>Atturney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> alſo hauing a care that a cauſe of ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that might aſwell ſtrike feare into the beſt Iudges, as ſore warne the corrupt (nay might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne any man that hath in any place or office but the power to diſcontent, ſo that no man can tel who ſhall ſuffer, and who ſhall looke on) ſhould not paſſe in any obſcure and ordinary manner, ſent for Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Sollicitor,</hi> and deſired him that he would be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided to make ſome declaration, ſuch as the cauſe required for the honour of Iuſtice, and for a note of diſtinction betweene ſo rare a cauſe and ordinarie matters of the Crowne.</p>
                  <p>Maiſter <hi>Atturney</hi> conceiuing at that time that the fact being ſo notorious and confeſſed vpon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Bartram</hi> would not haue pleaded <hi>not Guiltie:</hi> but it fell ſo out, that hee confeſſed not the Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but pleaded <hi>not Guiltie:</hi> whereupon the Iurie being not then ready at the Barre, further day was giuen for his triall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In</hi> the meane time, his Maieſty hearing of this ſtrange accident (as his manner is) was deſirous to penetrate into the roote and Center of this mans malice and fact: and in his Princely wiſedome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that this cruell murther muſt either ſpring from the inſtigation of others, or from <hi>Bartram</hi> himſelfe. And if from <hi>Bartram,</hi> it muſt proceed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:23837:10"/>
from an inueterate habite of a deſperate and wicked life: or for ſome vnſufferable wrong that Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall</hi> had done him, ſignified his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by the Lord <hi>Chamberlin</hi> vnto Maſter <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney;</hi> That there ſhould be ſome ſtay of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like proceeding, vntill <hi>Bartram</hi> were farther exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and directed the Examination to bee vpon three heads: Firſt, touching the Incitation: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, touching <hi>Bartrams</hi> courſe of life and Religion: and laſtly touching the Iuſtnes or Iniquity of Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndals</hi> report.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon Maſter Atturney calling Maſter Sollicitor to aſſiſt him, took the examination, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſend you a coppy, hauing obtained leaue of his Honor ſo to doe.</p>
                  <p>In which examination it plainely appeares, that the Diuell needed no Broker, but wrought imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly ypon the malice of the man, whoſe courſe and conuerſation of life was alwayes diſordered, and not without touch of <hi>Popiſh Religion;</hi> though it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be true that hee was a kind of Church-wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker in Weſtminſter, and came diuers times to heare either the ſeruice or the muſicke.</p>
                  <p>But for Sir <hi>Iohn Tyndall,</hi> he doth ſufficiently cleer him from bribery, either from being corrupted by his aduerſary, or tempted by himſelfe, and in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the cauſe hee had ſcarce a word in his mouth to impeach the report (as you may well perceiue, if
<pb facs="tcp:23837:11"/>
you compare his examination with the former rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this buſineſſe) in ſo much as both at that time hee did confeſſe, that it was one of the fouleſt murders that euer was committed.</p>
                  <p>And after hee ſaid to his vnder keeper, that the Kings Counſell (who had vſed him with much compaſſion towards his age and hurt) had cut ſore into the buſineſſe, as finding (belike) at that time ſome compunction, though it after vaniſhed as the morning cloud.</p>
                  <p>For notwithſtanding the Lord Chancellor had in great wiſdome giuen eſpeciall charge and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that cate ſhould be had of this man, as well for his body, as for his ſoule: For his body in 2. kindes, that his hurts ſhould bee looked to, and that hee ſhould be kept from doing himſelfe miſchiefe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once attempted it. And for his ſoule, that hee might haue ſome godly Preacher to bring him to the ſence of his ſinne (which is not ſo well diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the commitment of it, as in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it) and to ſaue him from impenitency: yet ſo was Gods will, that in the end he deſtroyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: but yet in that forme of execution which the Law and Iuſtice had preſcribed, and not by any other death, as he had formerly ſought to effect.</p>
                  <p>For on the ſeauenteenth day of this moneth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sunday</hi> in the morning, this man tooke occaſion to ſend away his keeper to fetch him a Bible for his
<pb facs="tcp:23837:11"/>
comfort, requiring that it might bee a latine Bible, and with a Concordance (thinking belike that ſuch a Bible was not ſo eaſie to be had) but there being one found in the houſe, and his keeper bringing it ſooner then he expected, hee ſent him againe for an <hi>Engliſh Bible,</hi> and that alſo being quickely returned vnto him, he ſaid he was not ſatiſfied with the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and deſired another Tranſlation, which hee thought was harder to get: and the better to winne time, told his keeper likewiſe that his ſtomacke was empty, and therefore deſired him to bring with him alſo ſome Ale, with a toſte: and in the meane time by a rope that he had gotten tied vnto a Tenter hooke, that was faſtened aboue the window to hang a hat on, hee hanged himſelfe, his legges almoſt trayling on the ground. The continuance of which deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate reſolution to make away himſelfe, the reaſon may bee gathered vpon ſome ſpeech he let fall at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times as I haue heard, that hee would bee ſorry to bee hanged in chaines: ſo that hee that had no ſence of preſeruing his life and ſoule, yet had apprehenſion and care of his ſenceleſſe Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo you haue here an end of this <hi>Tragedie,</hi> not preſuming to giue any iudgement, either of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious paſſions of theſe times, or of the dangers of Authoritie, or of the errors of Rumor, not to make any interpretation of the fact, or the circumſtances
<pb facs="tcp:23837:12"/>
thereof, but by this plaine declaration which I here ſend you, leaue the ſame to your meditations, who I am ſure deſires to know the truth herein, and who haue more leaſure, and will enter into them more ſincerely (perhaps) then we doe here in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>29. <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1616.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your aſſured Friend, <hi>N. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:12"/>
                  <p>The Examination of <hi>John Bartram,</hi> taken this 16. day of Nouember, 1616. before Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bacon</hi> his Maieſties Atturney Generall, and Sir <hi>Henry Yeluerton,</hi> his Maieſties Solicitor Generall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Beale.</hi> 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:13"/>
                  <head>Iohn Bartram,</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing asked whither after his diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment at the Report of Sir <hi>Io: Tindall</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Amy,</hi> hee did not vſe any words or ſpeeches to his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, or any priuate friend, whereby hee threatned the reuenge vpon Sir <hi>Io: Tindall,</hi> he proteſteth that as he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:23837:14"/>
comfort at his reſurrection, he did neuer vſe any ſuch ſpeeches to any perſon.</p>
                  <p>Being asked touching his Religion, he ſaith he is no Papiſt, nor euer was, but ſaith that hee was about <hi>20.</hi> yeares ſince indicted in the Kings bench by malice for Recuſancie, to which hee then pleaded his conformity, and was diſcharged thereby.</p>
                  <p>Being asked whether euer hee gaue or promiſed to giue to Sir <hi>Io: Tindall</hi> any money, reward, or gratuity in this Cauſe, he denyeth that euer he gaue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, or had at any time any ſpeech with him tending to any ſuch purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Being asked whether hee had any knowledge that Sir <hi>John Tindall,</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:23837:14"/>
Doctor <hi>Amy</hi> were corrupted or bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by his aduerſary to make the last Report, ſaith that hee doth not know it.</p>
                  <p>Being asked (the ſtate of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion being whether there were any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular bond or debt of <hi>200.</hi> pound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Harris</hi> and <hi>Chamberlin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides debts vpon Accompt, and vppon ſpecialtie amounting to that ſum) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee knew of any ſuch particular bond or not; he ſaith hee neuer ſaw any ſuch bond, nor knoweth it otherwiſe then by the recitall thereof made in the decree, and ſome Orders made in that Cauſe, and in a croſſe bill wherein (as he conceiueth) there is mention therof.</p>
                  <p>Being asked, whether hee be peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for his Fact, ſaith, that hee taketh
<pb facs="tcp:23837:15"/>
it to bee as foule a murder as euer was committed, and if he hath vttered any ſpeeches to the contrary he is very ſory for it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Bartram.</signed>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Examinatur coram</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Fra: Bacon.</item>
                           <item>Hen: Yeluerton.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23837:15"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
